<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The advice of Charles the Fifth, Emperor of Germany, and King of Spain, to his son Philip the Second upon his resignation of the crown of Spain to his said son.</title>
            <author>Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor, 1500-1558.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899260</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899260</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152882</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79401)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152882)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2330:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The advice of Charles the Fifth, Emperor of Germany, and King of Spain, to his son Philip the Second upon his resignation of the crown of Spain to his said son.</title>
                  <author>Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor, 1500-1558.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 163, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Mortlock, at the sign of the White Hart in Westminster-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  History --  Charles I, 1516-1556 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  History --  Philip II, 1556-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:2"/>
            <p>THE ADVICE OF <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, Emperor of <hi>GERMANY,</hi> AND KING OF SPAIN, To his Son <hi>Philip</hi> the Second; Upon his Reſignation of the Crown of <hi>SPAIN</hi> to his ſaid Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Mortlock,</hi> at the Sign of the White Hart in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Long preface to a little book, is a Giants head, on a Pigmies ſhoulders: This ſhall be ſo ſhort, as not to ſpend a line in promiſing bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. The following diſcourſe really contains <hi>Magnum in parvo;</hi> being of ſmall bulk, but treating of the greateſt Subject, Government: to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize it, I name the Author
<pb facs="tcp:152882:4"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> and King of <hi>Spain.</hi> That he was a perſon of as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted reaſon as quality; One Argument pertinent to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand ſhall ſerve, <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> that in the height of proſperity, and flouriſhing in reputation, He reſigned his Crowns to enjoy himſelf.</p>
            <p>That the day after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, was the firſt of his repentance, will appear to them who weigh the grandure of his ſpirit, and actions, a ſaying of more ſharpneſs than ſolid truth; and Calculated to the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of their thoughts, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring Crowns they never poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs, make their paſſions the meaſure of other mens Actions; and conclude no man can wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb facs="tcp:152882:4"/>part with what they ſo vehemently deſire. But the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of <hi>Charles</hi> having attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe altitudes others aſpire to, as the <hi>Ne plus ultra</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane happineſs; quitted them to mount into a higher ſphear. The <hi>Roman</hi> Empire ruined, (as it raiſed) it ſelf, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving awed all forreign hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties into ſubjection, or allyance; Employed againſt it ſelf, the ſtrength and reputation of its Arms; which had not left in the world an Enemy that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the honour, of falling by ſo vaſt a Power. <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth held it Greater Glory to Conquer himſelf, than the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he had ſubdued: and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Antagoniſt worthy his encounter, like the <hi>Roman</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152882:5"/>State, turned his force againſt himſelf; but with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that the <hi>Romans</hi> by Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil War, deſtroyed their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; <hi>Charles</hi> by conquering himſelf, in vanquiſhing thoſe ambitious paſſions which reign over Kings, and have Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors their vaſſals; by retyring from the Throne into an Ermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, obtained a Crown more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than that he reſigned: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diveſted himſelf of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral honours, to fit himſelf for inveſtiture in Caeleſtial Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</p>
            <p>But admitting that ſaying as true, as 'tis ſmart and piquante; and that he quitted his Crowns, for fear of loſing them; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogates not from the authority of his diſcourſe, nor diminiſhes
<pb facs="tcp:152882:5"/>the reputation of his wiſdom. For if he had Cauſe to fear the loſs of his Crowns, it argues greater prudence, by reſignation to make an happy <hi>Exit</hi> in full felicity; than to outlive his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, by ſeeing his Scepter wreſted out of his hand; and the glorious day of his ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did triumphs, ending in the diſmal Storms of War with his Son, like a new <hi>Phaeton</hi> juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Father out of the throne.</p>
            <p>The Diſcourſe is of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but preſumes not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct our Governours; and thought it may pleaſe the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the times, where Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are more inquiſitive into the duties of Soveraigns, than careful to practiſe their own,
<pb facs="tcp:152882:6"/>readier to learn what Princes ought to do, then to perform what Liegemen are bound to: and like the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat, ſtudy Law and policy, to teach others, not themſelves. 'Tis publiſhed to do it right, as worthy of publick view, and for publick advantage; For 'tis with men in ſociety, as with figures in Arithmetique; they receive their value from the place they ſtand in: but authority thought it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largeth the influence, doth not change the nature of perſons; as the figure that ſignifies a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, is the ſame as when it denotes One; the greateſt King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is but a Society made up of individuals, as the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt numbers are compoſed of
<pb facs="tcp:152882:6"/>the Digits, and the hugeſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the Letters of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet. The Emperour and his Subjects, being a grand Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as a Major and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty are a leſſer, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves into that of Maſters and Families; and they conſiſt of particular perſons, whereof eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is a Corporation in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; as made up of a mind to govern, and a body to obey. 'Tis a maxime in Philoſophy <hi>Simplicia Compoſitis priorca:</hi> And the model of Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was taken from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, where the Soul is Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign to direct and command; and the affections and members, are ſubjects to obey and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute. Thus private men are Princes; and have a harder Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,
<pb facs="tcp:152882:7"/>than the greateſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns: for thoſe luſts and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which are private mens Subjects, have reigned over Soveraigns, and conquered Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, who bridled Nations, and governed the greateſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities.</p>
            <p>Theſe are adviſes to Govern a Kingdom; but by the trick of <hi>Mutatis Mutandis,</hi> what was deſigned only for <hi>John</hi> at <hi>Noke,</hi> may be fitted for <hi>John</hi> at <hi>Styles:</hi> and what <hi>Charles</hi> delivered for a direction to order States, may ſerve you for inſtruction to govern your ſelf.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testament">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152882:7"/>
            <head>THE ADVICE OF <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, Emperour of <hi>GERMANY,</hi> To his Son <hi>Philip</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Spain:</hi> Upon the Reſignation of his Hereditary Crowns to his ſaid Son.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt dear Son,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NO Jewels appear ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as thoſe that embel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Crowns of Princes: Soveraignty is the Miſtreſs to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152882:8"/>which the Greateſt Spirits de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote their Services; Making the Univerſe a Theatre of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Actions, to Juſtifie their Title to the Dignity they Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. This hath made the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal State an Object of Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Envy to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; and given cauſe to Kings to think the Earth a Stage too narrow whereon to diſplay the Beams of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the Prerogatives of that Condition which hath no Equal under the Sun. This hath raiſed Ambition to that height, that Men trample on all Rights, Civil or Sacred, that obſtruct their paſſage to the Throne: And even deveſt themſelves of Humanity, in offering violence to the Laws
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152882:8"/>of Nature, that they may with more ſecurity put on and wear the Royal Purple; ſacrificing the Lives of neareſt Relations to the Intereſt of the Crown. Hence it is that the Examples of Quitting Crowns, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Scepters, are ſo rare, that ſucceeding Ages enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Relation thereof as Fancies, rather than Hiſtorical Truths. So natural to Man is the thirſt of Independant Freedom, that the Quitting of that which all deſire to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, ſeems a Paradox not to be eſteemed true in any Caſe, but Theirs, who by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity to uſe that Excellent Priviledge, are unworthy to enjoy it; or by pretending a Voluntary Reſignation, think
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152882:9"/>to palliate their Weakneſs, and hide their Diſability to hold that Scepter, which if not yielded, would be wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them. Like thoſe vain Sophiſts, who decried Riches, not out of a real Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of them, but becauſe they wanted them, and knew not how to gain them.</p>
            <p>The value of Gifts depends much on the Knowledge or Ignorance of the Donor, in proportion to which, it riſes and falls: The moſt magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Preſent from the hand of him that eſteems it mean, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes common, and lays on the Receiver an Obligation not anſwerable to the intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſique value of the Gift, but ſuitable to the Eſtimat of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152882:9"/>Giver, which like the Princes Stamp, often makes the ſame Piece Currant, at a higher and lower Rate: A Wedge of Gold beſtow'd by an Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, who thinks Glaſs more precious, deſerves only the ſmall Acknowledgements due for a Preſent of Glaſs, not of Gold. What I have ſaid of the Excellency of the Regal State, infers not an Alteration of my declared Reſolution to Refign my Diadems to you; but that as you ſhall receive a Gift of the Greateſt Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, it comes from my hand, who perfectly know the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendant value of what I give. And that you may ſee your Obligations to me, as my Bounty to you, equally ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152882:10"/>and read my Exceſs of Kindneſs for your Perſon, and high eſteem of your Abilities in the Character of that Love which hath engag'd me freely to transfer from my ſelf to you the Supreme Authority, to which the Greateſt Perſons in paſt Ages, have aſpired with that Ardency, and poſſeſſed with that Jealouſie, that Sons, Fathers, and Brothers fell Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctims to their Paſſions, for Gaining or Keeping the Throne; though they, if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of that Soveraign Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, would have redeemed with their own, the Lives of their Relations.</p>
            <p>That no Man Reſigns the Royal Power, but for Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to manage, or Fear to loſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152882:10"/>it, will be henceforth liſted in the Catalogue of Vulgar Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, upon the convincing Evidence of my ſingle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; who can without Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity call <hi>Europe, Aſia, Afri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> and <hi>America,</hi> to teſtifie my Ability to ſway and keep the Scepter in my hands; having fix'd ſo many recent Trophies of Conduct and Valour in theſe parts of the World, that the Antipodes muſt be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to find out an Enemy who may dare to attaque that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe Prudence and Proweſs have gain'd him the Honour to be rank'd amongſt the greateſt Heroes.</p>
            <p>Animals arrived at the years of maturity, are naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to preſerve their Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152882:11"/>by Propagation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Productions of their kind: It is my deſire, and will be my greateſt pleaſure, to ſee the exerciſe of theſe great Politique Vertues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous in my Actions, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by you; and to behold my Qualities and Dignities, as well as my Perſon, ſurvive my ſelf in you the Image of my Perſon, the actual Heir of my Dignities, and emulous Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of my Examples.</p>
            <p>The Sun, who in his Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian — Chariot guilds the World with glorious Beams, equally admirable as profitable to the Univerſe, withdraws at Night to reſt in the Curtains of his beloved <hi>Thetis;</hi> that Mortals, who prize good
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152882:11"/>things more by Privation than Fruition of them, may be taught by the Darkneſs that enſues his Retirement, to wiſh for and receive his morning Light with due Reſpect: I am now reſolved to confine my ſelf to the Privacies of a Religious Houſe, that the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ecclipſe of a Perſon whoſe Influence hath made this Empire and other States to flouriſh many years, may cauſe them to fix their Eyes on you, as the Riſing Sun; and with full Acclamations promiſe themſelves from your good Government, the continuance of that Happineſs they enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under mine: And look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, not as <hi>Philip</hi> the Son of <hi>Charles,</hi> but as <hi>Charles</hi> the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152882:12"/>Fifth, revived like a Phoenix out of his own Aſhes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the courſe of his youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Triumphs.</p>
            <p>That you may anſwer their Expectations, before I Reſign my Crowns into your hands, I ſhall give you ſome Directions which you are to eſteem as highly as theſe Diadems, which have derived their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtique Luſtre on my Head, from the Rules you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, more than from thoſe Orient Diamonds that adorn them.</p>
            <p>'Tis not my Intention to mind you here of thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Piety to God, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Magnanimity in your Actions, and Juſtice to your Subjects; which are the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152882:12"/>Baſis of Thrones, and Pillars of Soveraignty: For that I am ſatisfied by your Practice, that you have heartily embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thoſe Excellent Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of your Education: And that whether you converſe with the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nt or paſt Ages, you cannot want frequent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions by Men or Books, to urge the exerciſe of thoſe Fundamental Vertues. My Deſign is, to commend to your Obſervation ſome Rules and Maximes which my Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as Emperour and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> hath confirmed uſeful in the Government of thoſe States I ſhall Reſign into your Hands.</p>
            <p>When you conſider the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Dominions you are to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152882:13"/>ſucceed in, in <hi>Spain, Flanders, Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> with the different Conſtitutions and Inclinations of the People, the variety of their Laws and Politique Intereſts, you will preſently conclude, That great Governments are great Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens; and the Prerogatives you enjoy above other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are but Intimations and Marks of greater Cares and weightier Duties incumbent on you. The Cares of a Pilot are circumſcrib'd within the narrow Compaſs of the Ship he guides; but thoſe of an Admiral extend to the whole Fleet: The vigilance of other Princes, like the ſingle States they Rule, is ſhort and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; yours muſt be propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152882:13"/>to your Dominions, dilated from Eaſt to Weſt, and reach even to a New World. But that you may not be diſcouraged at the Troubles that attend your Greatneſs, Remember that as your Government is more Weighty and Large, ſo will your Glory be; which will run parallel with your Cares, and make you Renowned in thoſe Remote Regions where the Names of other Princes are never heard of.</p>
            <p>To adviſe a Great Prince to be content with the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he is born to, may ſeem ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to them who judge Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment a private Vertue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and extol an Inſatiable Ambition as the greateſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152882:14"/>of a King. But thoſe Rules of Juſtice that prohibit Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries between private Men, do ſo much the more oblige Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces not to violate the Rights of their weaker Neighbours, as the Conſequences of their Actions are more generally fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, involving not Families on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but Nations in Common Ruine; And as Princes, who are the Fountains, ought alſo to be the Examples of Juſtice to other Men. Beſides, I look on the Empire as ſwell'd to that Bulk, that to adde to it, were to cram meat into a full Stomach, which will not nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the Body, but oppreſs the Concoctive Faculty, and render it incapable to digeſt the Aliment it had received
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152882:14"/>before. Sure I am, it will be more acceptable with God, and pleaſing to men, for you to preſerve the Grandeur of your Eſtates by good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than by a wilde Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of New Conqueſts, to hazard your Hereditary Crowns.</p>
            <p>The Life of a Prince is like the Body of the Sun, which draws the Eyes of all Mortals towards him, and is as conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous as the Rays of Light: To think the bad Actions of a Prince can eſcape diſcovery, is to believe the Sun-Beams inviſible. 'Tis beneath your Dignity to do any thing that may fear the Cenſure, or not abide the Teſt of the whole World. And when you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152882:15"/>upon the Juriſdiction of Princes, that it extends only to the Hands and Tongues, but reaches not the Thoughts and Conceptions of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which are exempt from Earthly Powers, and triable in that Court only where the Gods of the Earth ſtand at the Bar to accompt for their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it will appear that though the bad Actions of a Prince may eſcape the Laſh of his Subjects Tongues, and the violence of Revenge, they will be certainly Arraigned, Sentenc'd, and Condemned in their private Thoughts, which fear not the Rigor of Humane Laws, nor the Treacherous Malice of Informers. And the Sentences pronounced
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152882:15"/>there, will be readily execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when a fit occaſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes Indempnity; and with ſo much the more eagerneſs and virulency as their former fear to expreſs their Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces was great: Like hidden Fires, that burſt forth in more violent Eruptions. The end of this Diſcourſe, is, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to ſuch a Comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as becomes your Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and may ſatisfie your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that they are happy under your Conduct, by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Security they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from your Care and Vigilance, in recompence of thoſe Duties of Subjection and Obedience they pay you. This will beget an intire Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence on their part in your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152882:16"/>Prudence and Goodneſs, and eſtabliſh your Throne in the Hearts and Affections of your People. And though it be much controverted whether Princes are more ſecure in the Love or Fear of their People, I commend it to you as my ſence, That the ſecurity of Government depends more on the Love than Fear of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: And take it as my Advice to chooſe the way of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Clemency to make your Throne durable, rather than that of Violence and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, to render your ſelf more abſolute; but withal to entail the hatred of the People on your Poſterity. How fatal it hath been to Princes to preſs their People with exceſſive
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152882:16"/>ſeverities, appears by thoſe Examples, where the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Old, forceth the People to entertain thoughts of New Maſters; who are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting to invite them to Diſloyalty, by Promiſes of Eaſe and better Uſage: And the People, willing to believe what they paſſionately wiſh, are eaſily perſwaded to change that Condition than which they think none can be worſe.</p>
            <p>It is a vain Opinion, That the Security of Governours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the Poverty or Slavery of their <hi>People,</hi> whom you muſt deveſt of Humanity, before you can render them ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of thoſe Preſſures and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries that attend a needy and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152882:17"/>ſervile Condition; nor is it poſſible for men under Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Miſeries, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Eaſe and Happineſs. And how frequent opportunities a Politique Body may have to attain their deſires in this kind, is ſufficiently illuſtrated by the hatred that attends Tyranny, the natural itch of Innovation, and Subtleties of Ambitious Men, who never fail to improve all occaſions to raiſe their Fortunes on the Ruines of their Superiours.</p>
            <p>It is the happineſs of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the things which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally procure the Love of the People, are alſo moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the practice of the Prince: And that it is their Intereſt to exerciſe thoſe Vertues which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152882:17"/>they are obliged to embrace for their Native Beauty and Excellency, though Naked and Deſtitute of Forraign Advantages. What can more become a Prince, than the Religious obſervance of Faith, Continence, and Juſtice? And what can more endear him in the Affections of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, than the practice of theſe Vertues, which will infallibly beget an intire Confidence in his Goodneſs, a hearty Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Love for his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a ſincere Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reverent Regard for his Perſon and State: Faith in your proceedings, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Word, will gain Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to your Promiſes at home and abroad; and the reſpects
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152882:18"/>due to a Generous and Noble Prince, whoſe Word hath ſome reſemblance with that of God, which never deceives them that rely on it. Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence will make your Perſon venerable; and beſides the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of your good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will convince your People of the excellency of your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, who being above the power of Law, are a Law to your ſelf; and by a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Election and generous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Goodneſs, can keep within due bounds that unruly Paſſion which hath left a ſtain on the Names of the greateſt Monarchs, and the Severity of Laws and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of Puniſhments cannot regulate in meaner men;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152882:18"/>whom you can then freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of thoſe Vices, which if guilty your ſelf, you could not without Bluſhing rebuke in others. Your Juſtice will fill your Dominions with Men of Worth and Merit, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Way to Honours and Preſerments open only through the Temple of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, will become Votaries to Goodneſs, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from your Juſtice the Rewards due to excellent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and eſcape thoſe Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments and Diſgraces your juſt Severity inflicts on Vice and Wickedneſs. Theſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues will implant in your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Minds ſuch Eſteem for your Perſon, and Opinion of your Goodneſs, that when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152882:19"/>any miſcarriage in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment happens by Injuſtice, or otherwiſe, they will impute it to the failings of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; Judging it as impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for you to deviate from your Juſtice and Goodneſs, as the Sun to vary his conſtant Courſe.</p>
            <p>The Affairs of Princes are divided between Peace and War, which have their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Ways and diſtinct Rules of Management, and afford Occaſions for the Exerciſe of different Vertues: It is the prudence of a Prince to make the one ſubſervient to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and in the Sun-ſhine of Peace to provide for the Storms of War, which is a time of Expence, as the other
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152882:19"/>is of Gain: Both have proper and peculiar Arts, wherein the dexterity of a Prince is much ſeen, in uſing both to beſt advantage. And as the beſt end of War, is Peace; ſo a wiſe Prince in the Securities of a deep Peace, hath War in proſpect.</p>
            <p>The certain Charge that attends the Conduct of great States, is ſo vaſt, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergencies that may require extraordinary Expence, ſo frequent and various, that Frugality and good Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry juſtly claim an honourable place in the Quire of Royal Vertues, it being impoſſible to act thoſe great things that become a Prince, and make Thrones Renowned, without
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152882:20"/>a ſtock of money to ſupply their Occaſions; the proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, as it denominates a Prince frugal and prudent, ſo it ſtrikes terror into his Enemies, procures reſpect from his Allies, reverencee from his Subjects, and lies in readineſs to ſerve his Glory: Whereas Contempt is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable Companion of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, though ſitting in a Throne, and adorn'd with a Diadem.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſtep to make your ſelf rich, is to make your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo; and that your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure may be full, endeavour that theirs may abound and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-flow. Let it be your principal care to ſecure their Traffique, and protect them in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152882:20"/>their Commerce. This, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the advantage of your Exchequer by your Cuſtoms, will win you the Affections of your People, whom nothing pleaſeth more than the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Wealth, which makes them eſteem him the beſt Prince under whom they thrive moſt. The improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Eſtates is a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefit and effect of your Protection, and an Argument ſo convincing and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of good Government, that they yield a voluntary and chearful obedience to that Regiment from which they derive ſuch real and palpable advantages; and will eſteem it a Priviledge, not a Burden, to obey. When you are thus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152882:21"/>become Maſter of their hearts, you may at a pinch command their Purſes, who cannot but hold themſelves obliged in good Nature and Intereſt, to part with a pittance to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his Neceſſities, to whoſe Care and Protection they owe their Abundance; and may expect an increaſe of their ſtore, by the Continuance of his Favour, as their denyal may incline him by remiſsneſs and neglect of their Concerns, to expoſe what they profeſs to hazard and danger; and daſh all hopes of future im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement.</p>
            <p>It will be a ſingular means to gain Eſteem and Love from your People, if you make Proviſion of Neceſſaries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152882:21"/>times of Dearth; And by affording them at reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rates for Relief of their Wants, it will appear to them that you prefer publique Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction before your private Benefit: And the Reputation of your prudent Fore-ſight and Care for their Good, will implant in them a ſolid Love for your Perſon, and Eſteem for your Conduct, than which nothing can be of more advantage in the Courſe of your Affairs. No Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits leave ſo deep impreſſions as thoſe that come ſeaſonably for Relief of Neceſſities; which being a clear Evidence of your Love to your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, will beget a reciprocal Love from them. 'Tis vain
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152882:22"/>to think a Grieved People can be Courted to forget their Miſeries by Sports and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes, or fooled out of the memory of their Sufferings, into Affection to their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, by Shews and Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which may for a moment pleaſe the fancy; but work not any other Effects than meerly ſuperficial, as light and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as vain and tranſitory, as their Cauſes: The Bonds of Policy are real and ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and Subjection a ſerious thing, which affects ſo deeply the Hearts of Men, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſenſible Effects of a viligant Protection, derived to them by ſolid Advantages from their ſuperiours, can make them love thoſe Chains
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152882:22"/>which Nature abhors.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Neceſſities of State may often force you to preſs your People to extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Supplies, by Taxes and Impoſitions; you are to conſider that the power of a Prince depends upon his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Conformity to his Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and uniform aſſent to ſerve and honour him. And inaſmuch as nothing touches them more nearly in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Fortunes (the Blood of the People) than the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of New Aids, that Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Mean which is the beſt Rule of Humane Actions, is to be obſerved accurately in theſe Affairs: And you are to take ſpecial heed not to ſtrain the ſtrings of your Power too
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152882:23"/>high, to prevent thoſe Jars and Diſcords that uſually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order the whole harmony of Government on theſe occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And though in this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I may ſeem to contradict my own practice, having often burdened my People with Taxes and Impoſitions; I have this to juſtifie my Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that I never took that Courſe, but forced by indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable neceſſities of my Wars, nor made uſe of it but againſt my Will; and that I never had encouragement from the effects it wrought in my Peoples Hearts to reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the practice.</p>
            <p>To give you ſome Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a matter of ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I obſerve that Moneys
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152882:23"/>are drawn by Princes from their Subjects two ways, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary and compulſive: I call that voluntary, when the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject does, as by Contract, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>quid pro quo</hi> from his Soveraign, in ſome particular Benefit, for the Money he pays; as in the ſale of Offices, farming of Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive, when no particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence is made by the Prince for what he receives, and the Subjects Money exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from him: for though in truth, when Taxes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are raiſed to ſerve Publique Neceſſities, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed accordingly, the <hi>Prince</hi> is but the <hi>Peoples</hi> Steward, to diſpoſe of their Aids for their benefit, wherein they receive
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152882:24"/>the recompence of their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies: Yet theſe Benefits being commonly remote, general, and diffuſive, paſs as it were inviſible and unperceived, by the particular Members of the Body politique, who are little affected with any Advantage, but what ſenſibly accrues to them in their private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns. This is the reaſon why this later ſeems ſo harſh, and the other pleaſant to the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> and may incline you to uſe this, rather than that. The Court of <hi>Rome</hi> may encourage all <hi>Princes</hi> ſtudious of their profit, to eſtabliſh the ſale of Offices, as a great Help to fill their Treaſures; which is clearly proved by the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Papacy:</hi> for be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152882:24"/>the Church never ſo poor in the Vacancy of the See, the ſucceeding Pope never fails to furniſh himſelf abundantly in the very entrance of his reign by this ſingle means of the ſale of Offices.</p>
            <p>That other way of Supply by Taxes and Impoſitions, is not ſo odious, but by dextrous management, diſcreet Officers, and preſidents of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys under heavier Burdens, it may be practiſed without inconvenience. But it will concern the <hi>Prince</hi> by eaſie Acceſs, kind Reception, ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Anſwers, and obliging Carriage, and by making out the Neceſſities that occaſion this Grievance, to ſweeten the Affections of the people into
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152882:25"/>a Belief that he hath not taken this courſe willingly, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by urgent Occurents of State, and for the defence or other advantage of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And in levying theſe Impoſitions, whether tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or perpetual, have a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eye on your Officers, leſt by Exactions and Violences they adde to the <hi>Peoples</hi> miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and render them leſs able to furniſh you another time.</p>
            <p>Never impoſe high Cuſtoms on thoſe things which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported or exported to ſerve the Neceſſities of the place; for in that caſe the moderate Cuſtom makes the greater vent, and proves more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious than heavy Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which diſcourage Trade,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152882:25"/>and not onely deprive the place of Neceſſaries for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, but ſtop the ſale of thoſe Superfluities it can ſpare, by the thin reſort of forraign Merchants, where Great Cuſtoms devour the Gains of thoſe that Traffique. To impoſe high Cuſtoms on forraign Superfluities impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is not only juſt, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them that affect thoſe Novelties pay dear for their Fancies, but in deterring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the vanity of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on thoſe Trifles the Moneys that may be otherwiſe better employed.</p>
            <p>Allow convenient time for payment of your Taxes, and let them be gathered by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers, not new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152882:26"/>whoſe violence commonly exaſperates the people to the danger of the State. In a word, chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pawn or ſell part of your Revenue to ſupply your Occaſions, than by encreaſing the peoples Burdens, to force them to a deſire of Change. And when Neceſſity leaves no other way open, conſider the nature of the places you Tax, what they can beſt furniſh you withal; as <hi>Spain,</hi> with Money; <hi>Germany,</hi> Men; <hi>Italy,</hi> both Money and Men. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ingratiate your ſelf with the people by a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Remiſſion of part of the Aſſeſsments; and let all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Grace flow to them immediately from your ſelf,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152882:26"/>and refer to your Miniſters what is harſh and odious. Above all, ſee that what is ſo dearly purchaſed with the peoples groans and your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, be brought to your Purſe, and not diverted to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate profit of your Officers. Keep Credit with the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, protect them in their Trade, and ſecure their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Genoa,</hi> whoſe Loans you will find uſeful in many Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which may require quicker ſupplies than can be raiſed by the ordinary ways of Tax and Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>The abſolute neceſſity of an able Council, is evidently gathered from the impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of diſpatching the Affairs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152882:27"/>of State, by a ſingle perſon, though of prodigious Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: And that ſeveral Princes of diſſolute Lives, and weak Capacities, have reigned with honour to the State, and to the ſatisfaction of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, meerly by the prudence and faithfulneſs of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; to whom the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Princes owe moſt of their Glory, as the <hi>Atlas</hi>'s of their Government, on whoſe ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders they are triumphantly carried through the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Policy, into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Immortal Honour.</p>
            <p>Your Wiſdom cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in any thing more, than in the choice of fit perſons to ſerve you in your weighty Affairs, by Counſel and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152882:27"/>And the better to guide your Election, think no man worthy employment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you, but ſuch whoſe Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom enables them to diſcharge their Truſt to beſt advantage, and ſecure them from thoſe Inconveniencies wherein men are involved by Ignorance and Imprudence. And leſt paſſion or intereſt ſhould incline them to employ their Talents to your prejudice; and ſtudy their own, more than your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Honour: Your next care muſt be, That their Wiſdom be attended with a generous Faithfulneſs to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their Truſt, intire Love for your <hi>Perſon,</hi> and a vertuous Diſpoſition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, it will be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152882:28"/>to give the people ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when the ſcandalous Lives of your Miniſters ſhall give them cauſe to ſuſpect all their Actions, and to preſage nothing but Ruine to the State from their Conduct who cannot govern themſelves. Tis an excellent Secret, and one of the prime Myſteries in the Art of Government, for a <hi>Prince</hi> incapable to manage Affairs of State, to cover his Defects by employing men of Excellent Abilities, well-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and faithful to his Crown. The Glory of their Actions redounds to the <hi>Prince;</hi> and the people, never curious to enquire from what hand they receive their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, reſt ſo well ſatified
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152882:28"/>with the Effect, that they care not to pry into the Cauſe, but applaud him an Excellent <hi>Prince,</hi> under whom they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy peace and plenty, though perhaps he contributes little to the Felicity they live in.</p>
            <p>The Advantages of Honour and Profit that attend the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Princes,</hi> attract multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes to ſeek and preſs for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; but you are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that moſt of theſe men come to ſerve their ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and covetous Humours, not the Intereſt and Honour of the State. But as I will not condemn all that catch at em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and offer their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, ſo I adviſe you to think your beſt diligence well laid out, to find men in all places
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152882:29"/>of your Dominions, fit to ſerve you; and having found them, to eſteem your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Wealth and Honour never better expended than in encouraging ſuch men by am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Rewards, and obliging them more ſtrictly to your perſon and intereſt: The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that the World affords numbers of excellent perſons, who in private For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes have princely Spirits, elevated to that pitch, that they admire not Riches or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but prefer the Liberty of an obſcure Retirement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſplendid Servitude of high Employments. Yet theſe men, when drawn forth to appear on the Theatre of State, have acted their parts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152882:29"/>with ſingular Dexterity, incomparable Integrity, and admired Courage. And ſettle it for a Maxime, That in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of importance, a prudent and couragious Counſellor may promote your deſigns by his ſound Advice, more than Legions of Souldiers, and whole Mountains of Treaſure. And you may obſerve that the greateſt <hi>Princes</hi> in all Ages have made choice of, and been ſerved by the ableſt Miniſters; whereof <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the greateſt <hi>Prince</hi> in my Judgement, for Peace and War, that ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared on the Stage of the World, is a ſufficient Inſtance; No Age having produced a <hi>Prince</hi> equal to him, or a <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> Miniſters comparable to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152882:30"/>thoſe he employ'd. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is obvious, <hi>Like will to like:</hi> And a gallant <hi>Prince</hi> preſently diſcovers the Weakneſs of a Miniſter, and ſlights him; as a weak <hi>Prince</hi> comprehends not the Excellencies, and therefore ſeldom uſes the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of an able Officer.</p>
            <p>'Tis uſeful and neceſſary to obſerve the Genius of your Officers, and fit them with Employments ſuitable to their Inclinations and particular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies: For a Miniſter who may perform Excellent Services to your Crown in <hi>Spain,</hi> if employed in <hi>Italy</hi> may prejudice your Affairs there, which are to be carried on with other Maximes, and manag'd by perſons of tempers
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152882:30"/>different from your <hi>Spaniſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</hi> In the choice of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals and Captains of Armies, this Rule is of ſingular benefit, which may appear by that eminent Example of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> inferiour to none in Conduct or Succeſs in Land-Wars, but moſt unhappy in Naval En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements: So rare a thing is a man abſolutely wiſe, that can at all times, in all places, and on all occaſions, merit the praiſe of a dextrous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</p>
            <p>Leſt the date of your Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs expire with the Lives of your able Counſellors, fail not to train up others for your ſervice, in the life-time and under the tuition of your greateſt Miniſters, to be a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152882:31"/>Nurſery of gallant perſons, whoſe eminent Abilities and worthy Actions, may perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate the Felicity of your Eſtates. Take the Romans for your Example, who to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Inconvenience might enſue the leaving the ſtreſs of their great Affairs, to rely and depend on the Life of a ſingle perſon, in all their Armies made proviſion of ſeveral able Commanders aſſigned to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the Office of General, in caſe of miſadventure to the perſon actually officiating the Chief Charge.</p>
            <p>Never hazard matters of Importance in a time of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, upon their management, who were never employed in Affairs of equal weight: In
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152882:31"/>which Caſes you are to prefer the experience of your Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, before the Humours of your younger Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors.</p>
            <p>'Tis a common Obſervation that young men are generally bold and credulous, as old men fearful and ſuſpitious; therefore in the choice of Counſellors, reſpect chiefly the middle Age, as a mean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe Extreams: But rely moſt on their Advice, who have given proof of their ſufficiency in dangerous occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and are grown gray with the Cares of Government; whoſe Experience may tune the diſſonant Humours of jarring Councils to a perfect Harmony: But think not I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152882:32"/>exclude young or old men from your Councils, for the Common Obſervation like General Rules hath its excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in many Inſtances of young men of ripe Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and old ones of flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Wits and warm Courage. I rather commend to your imitation that Roman Medley where the heat of young men was tempered by the cool and ſtaid prudence of gray-heads, and the quinteſſence of both concurred in men of middle Age, who partaking of the vigorous Heat of the former, and ſober Wiſdom of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, were excellent both for Counſel and Execution, and together made up the Body of a Roman Senate.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152882:32"/>
            <p>The Ancient Greeks, in four famous Examples, have intimated to us four ſpecial means to attain Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>The firſt by Experience: Expreſſed in the Story of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamemnon</hi> and <hi>Menelaus,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as perſons grown wiſe by variety of Buſineſs, and Obſervations gathered out of frequent Audiences, Treaties, and Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is by Hiſtories and Memories, which in ſmall Volumns comprehending the Tranſactions of many Ages, afford Inſtructions uſeful in Occurrences of the preſent Times, and furniſh the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with Examples of all ſorts, diſcovering not only the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152882:33"/>of former Times, but the Cauſes of them; and ſhewing thoſe Rocks on which unskilful Pilots have ſplit the Ship of State, direct the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Obſerver to ſteer his Courſe into a ſafe Port. This we have figured in <hi>Solon</hi> and <hi>Socrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third by Travel into forraign Countreys to mark the variety of Laws, of Policy, which may be uſeful in Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences at home, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth in <hi>Neſtor,</hi> by long Life, where one Leſſon learnt yearly, ſwells at laſt to a Syſtem of Wiſdom. When all theſe concur in one perſon, they make his perſon reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, and his Counſels Oracles.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152882:33"/>
            <p>Nor will it be unſafe to rely on their Advice, who have joyned Hiſtorical to Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Wiſdom: And though the length of time ſuppoſed neceſſary to attain theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſorts of Wiſdom, ſeem to exclude young men from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſters of any of them, yet a young Prince may ſoon attain them all, by frequent converſe by the Eminent in every kind, and diſcreet uſe of their Counſels.</p>
            <p>The ſecond qualification of a Miniſter, is, That he be a Good Man: Where the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit Arts of Hypocriſie, thoſe inviſible Deceits and Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths in the hearts of Men, have made it almoſt impoſſible to pronounce a right Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152882:34"/>without long and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Obſervation of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: for Actions may be good in Subſtance and Effect, yet not denominate the Agent a Good Man, becauſe they may be done with a bad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, or ill deſigns, or by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, or may proceed from a wavering mind, not out of Love to Vertue, but to ſerve its Intereſt, or gratifie it ſelf with more eaſe and ſecurity in ſome corrupt Luſt, or vitious Practice; to promote which, the ſame perſon will by and by act things quite contrary to the good now done. He only deſerves the Title of a Good Man, who having well weigh'd the Pleaſures and Profits that court men to Vice,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152882:34"/>makes a deliberate Election, and gives the preference to Vertuous Courſes, being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied he hath an abſolute Obligation to Truth and Goodneſs, deveſted of all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular advantages: Acts well, out of a Generous Principle, That 'tis his Duty to do ſo, and improves this Principle by conſtant Practice into an habitual Goodneſs: This is that fix'd immoveable Man, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who muſt ceaſe to be, before he can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate from the Rules of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Prefer this qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in your Miniſter, before Riches, Favour, and all the Goods of Fortune; which if they want, let them be furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by you, in reward of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152882:35"/>their Services; the rather, for that the meaner his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was whom your Bounty exalts, the ſtronger will the Obligation be, and his grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude greater. That favour is moſt acceptable, which is proper and agreeable to the humour of him on whom it is beſtowed: Therefore you are to diſpence your Bounties in Honours, Profits, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as moſt ſuitable to their various Inclinations. And let not your Favourites or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers deprive you of any part of that Gratitude which is due to your Bounty, which they will certainly do, if your favours flow not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from your ſelf, but are got upon their motion and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152882:35"/>intreaty, or conferr'd by their hands.</p>
            <p>Scorn to be ſo much your Favourites or Domeſticks Servant, as to confine your ſelf always to their Advice in what concerns your Family or Perſon, but uſe your Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to take Counſel, where your Reaſon ſuggeſts the beſt may be had; and prefer the Conſiderations of Wiſdom and Vertue, not onely to thoſe of Riches and Honour, but the neareſt Relations of Domeſticks, or Favourites, not commended by the ſame qualities to your ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
            <p>Cheriſh Emulation in your Miniſters, by giving aſſured Hopes of Nobler Rewards to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152882:36"/>the better deſert, but take heed this Emulation between them proceed not to Jealouſie, and perpetual Diſlikes, as very prejudicial to your ſervice in the Claſhings of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Actions, and in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy that attends the Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt Meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which involves the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in perpetual Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and engages him to le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel all his Deſigns more to croſs and leſſen the others Authority, and traduce his Services, than to promote your Intereſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis a common Error in <hi>Princes</hi> of great Parts not to conſult with, or to neglect the Advice of their ableſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, leſt theſe ſhould claim
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152882:36"/>a ſhare in the Glory of their Actions, and rob them of part of that Honour which they would intirely enjoy: For ſince the Advice of Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors depends ſo much on the Reſolution of the Prince, what reaſon is there, but that the Prince may juſtly aſſume the intire Glory of the Action, though proceeding from his Miniſters Advice; which, if not actuated by the Prince, had remained a formleſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Embryon, without Beauty or Efficacy? As the Architect carries the Honour of the Edifice, though the Model was framed with the Advice of a Labourer. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, you may make great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of ſounding the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152882:37"/>of your Counſellors, without imparting to them the Secret of your Deſigns.</p>
            <p>What is ſaid of Counſellors, will be of uſe in your choice of Governours of Provinces, Towns, and Places of ſtrength. I will adde onely this, That I hold it moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for the Prince to grant ſuch Offices for ſome ſhort time only, to prevent the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of making Parties, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on diſloyal Deſigns; which the Opportunities of a long continuance in Office may tempt ambitious Spirits to. Nor can frequent Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of this kind diſpleaſe the People, who are naturally ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Novelty, and apt to nauſeate things accuſtomed,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152882:37"/>though never ſo Good.</p>
            <p>Eaſie Acceſs, and free Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, are great Obligations to the Commons; eſpecially when you apply Remedies to the Grievances they complain of; and by the ſame means you will gain great Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Experience in buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and an inſight into a thouſand Deſigns, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe you had never heard of.</p>
            <p>The like, and many other good effects will attend the Progreſſes you are to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſeveral parts of your Dominions; but take heed the frequency of them render them not contemptible, nor the Charge burdenſom to your Subjects. As they muſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152882:38"/>not be too long intermitted, leſt hope of impunity move your Deputies and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to oppreſs the People, and their hopes of Relief from the preſence of their Prince, be extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>Receive Petitions courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, hear patiently, expreſs Compaſſions to thoſe in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and endeavour that none may depart unſatisfied from your preſence. See that the Power of Great Ones weigh not down the Right of the Poor. And in giving of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſpect not for the time, the good or ill report of the Perſons, but the merits of the Cauſe. Confer Offices of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature on Perſons of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Integrity. And to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152882:38"/>them to diſcharge their Duties well, give them cauſe to believe that the firſt ſtep to higher Dignities, is to behave themſelves well in the lower.</p>
            <p>Conſcience and Charity o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige to a ſpecial regard of Churches, Orphans, Widows, Priſoners, Captives, and all Perſons in miſery and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; fail not to relieve them with expedition in their Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And ſettle it in your mind as an undoubted Truth, That God, who judges all without reſpect of Perſons, hath declared himſelf pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe and ready to hear the Cries of the Diſtreſſed, and will certainly puniſh thoſe Kings and States, where ſuch
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152882:39"/>Cauſes are ſlighted, or ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to Power or Affection: Which I could clear to you by Examples in the compaſs of my Experience; but that your Piety and Tenderneſs of Conſcience make it ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to adde more on this point.</p>
            <p>The like expedition is to be uſed in the Cauſes of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and other men, who loſe more by ſpending time in attending the tedious and chargable formality of <hi>Courts,</hi> than the matters in difference amount to in value.</p>
            <p>Diſpatch in perſon what Cauſes you can, the reſt refer to your Officers; to whom you are for expedition to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſeverally their proper Tasks.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:152882:39"/>
            <p>In capital matters, temper Severity with Lenity, and incline rather to abſolve a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Criminal, than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn an Innocent Perſon, but let not your Lenity be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive, as to encourage Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. Weigh ſeriouſly the circumſtances of Perſons, Times, and Places; and hold not your ſelf ſo obliged to the ſtrict obſervance of the dead Letters of your Laws, but that on juſt grounds you may diſpenſe with the Rigor of thoſe puniſhments they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict. Frame your Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings by the <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule, ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the variety of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; for then only the people have juſt cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain that Juſtice is not equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152882:40"/>adminiſtred againſt Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, when they ſee the ſame Crime in ſeveral perſons une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually puniſhed, but cannot diſcern any Reaſon of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</p>
            <p>However, have ſuch reſpect to the majeſty of your Laws, that the power of Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may remain in your ſelf incommunicable to any, but by ſpecial Commiſſion on weighty Occurrences: And in theſe Caſes, Governours of States are the beſt Judges to moderate Laws, who ſee thoſe Reaſons to incline them, which paſs the Knowledge, and exceed the Capacity of ordinary Advocates: But be ſure this moderation ariſe out of a Right in Equity,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152882:40"/>not Errour in Affection.</p>
            <p>Let no Service done you paſs unrewarded; at leaſt in good words, which may beget an expectation of real Benefit, when time ſerves. Be not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to inquire into the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Actions of your Subjects, but let it ſatisfie you that they live conformable to your Laws, without ſcandal and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt offence to the majeſty of your Government. Leave ſecret faults to his Judgement who ſearches the heart, and ſees all things: What reaſon is there our hands ſhould exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, where the Eye cannot pierce. Beware of prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Opinions, and ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve an Ear for the other ſide in matters of complaint:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152882:41"/>Encourage not undue Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by too much Facility, nor diſcourage juſt Addreſſes by a Rigor that may preclude all expectation of Reaſon from you of your proceedings.</p>
            <p>Never paſs ſentence in Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or any other perturbation, leſt you give juſt Cauſe, as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> of Appeal from your ſelf, blinded with Paſſion, to your ſelf ſeeing with the Eye of Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Let the Guards of your Perſon be ſo kept about you, that it may appear done more to ſet forth the majeſty of Government, than out of any neceſſity to ſecure your Life.</p>
            <p>To uſe Princely Garments ſometimes, begets Reverence
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152882:41"/>for your Perſon, and ſtrikes Awe into the Multitude; but generally to wear a plain Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit fitted to the Mode of the Country, procures much love; the Subject being much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obſerve in their Prince a careleſs contempt of thoſe Complements in which others vainly place their principal felicity: Obſerve the like Rule in your Diet; neither incurring hatred from the people by Exceſs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs; nor Contempt, by ſinking too near the condition of a Subject.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point, the time of Peace is moſt fit for adorning Cities, repairing High-Ways and Bridges, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Rivers Navigable, build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152882:42"/>
               <hi>Churches,</hi> Hoſpitals, Guild-Halls, reforming Abuſes in Religion, viſiting Univerſities, <hi>Colledges,</hi> and <hi>Courts</hi> of Juſtice, Education of Orphans, Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of poor Maids, Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Priſoners, and other Works of publique Benefit, which will oblige the People to Love and Thankfulneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Monuments to Poſterity of your Goodneſs, and happy Reign, and crown you with Eternal Glory.</p>
            <p>As the Tempeſts and Storms of bluſtering Winter, do by natural Revolution ſucceed the ſerene and calm Summer Seaſon; So the tranquility of the ſecureſt Peace, does by the Politique Viciſſitude and Circulation of Affairs, end in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152882:42"/>the Troubles of War, by a neceſſity immutable as the Laws of Nature. But my preſent Buſineſs is not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Truth of this Sepeculation, but to direct your Conduct in Military Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, by Rules approved by my long experience in ſeveral Wars of greateſt importance.</p>
            <p>The Skill of a Pilot is not ſeen in the Halcyon Dayes of fair Weather, when a rude Seaman in a Cock-Boat can lead a Dance for a whole Fleet to ſport ſecurely on the ſmiling Ocean; but when the angry Marine Gods in a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful defiance, ſwelling their huge Waves unto the Clouds, threaten to throw back thoſe Waters into the face of <hi>Jove,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:152882:43"/>which he had ſhowred down to make a diſdained Addition to the liquid Element. The Ship of State is eaſily guided in Times of Peace, when all Diſcontents are huſht into an intire Obedience to the Laws, and no Diſturbance nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention appears, but what ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes out of Mens Emulation to conform to their Princes Wills: To ſteer an even and ſteddy Courſe to your deſired Port, through the Audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tumults of Popular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections confronting your Authority, the violences of Forraign Enemies, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque your Power; as it will try your Prudence and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſo it is always attended with the Glory due to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152882:43"/>Conduct, and will crown your Head with the Immortal Lawrels of a Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Conquerour.</p>
            <p>Directions are ſo much the more neceſſary for the Affairs of War, than Peace, as the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of War are more vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and unexpected, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct thereof more uncertain, and ſubject to alteration on all ſudden Occurrences; and the Errors irrecoverable, or not to be redeemed without much Damage and Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Nor can a Prince give better proof of his Vertue and Goodneſs, than by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in time of War, when Cuſtom ſeems to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and Power tempts him to all licentiouſneſs, when
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152882:44"/>Ambition prompts him to break through the Spider Web of Legal Bonds, and ſcorn any Rule of his Deſires or Actions, but the Dictates of his Will; And his Sword promiſes ſecurity againſt the weak oppoſition of the tame Arts and unarmed Rights of Peace.</p>
            <p>As the Majeſty of your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire will certainly expoſe you to the Envy of Chriſtian States, the Jealouſie of the Turk, and the Enmity of both; So it will render War a matter not of Conveniency only, to purge your Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of thoſe ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that may moleſt, and corrupt Members which may deſtroy ſo great a Body, but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152882:44"/>of abſolute neceſſity for your Intereſt, that you may never be unprovided of powerful Forces and expert Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to ſerve your deſigns of inlarging your Empire, and to ſecure you againſt all Attempts oſ Forreign Power, and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Subjects, to which ſo great and divided a Dominion as yours, is as ſubject by the various Humours, Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Intereſts of its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and the buſie Arts of your Neighbours, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Air to ſtorms and tempeſts, by the buſtling vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of Winds and Vapours. Beſides, there is juſt cauſe to fear that the diſuſe of Arms, will no leſs weaken and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Body Politique, than
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152882:45"/>want of motion the Elemental Subſtances: And it will be very difficult to bring them back to endure patiently the Hardſhips of War, who have drunk deep of the delicious Nectar of Eaſe and Reſt, and enjoyed the ſoft Pleaſures of Peace, or to keep them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Bounds of Civil Laws, who have been long uſed to the Licentiouſneſs of War: For as Martial Diſcipline ſeems too rigid and ſevere to thoſe, ſo the Experience of ſeveral great Monarchies hath confirmed, that the Threats of Humane Edicts cannot deterr them from purſuing their Luſts in deſpite of Laws, the firſt Principle of whoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, is, <hi>Not to fear;</hi> and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152882:45"/>whoſe Converſation with Death the King of Terrors, hath made the Loſs of Life ſo familiar and contemptible, that like them who by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant uſe of Poyſons, have exempted themſelves from the fatal effects thereof; Thoſe Capital Puniſhments which appear to others as Bug-bears to fright them from tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Limits of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have no operation on their tougher Conſtitutions, who having often expoſed their Lives to utmoſt perils, meerly to ſerve the intereſts of their Leader, will not ſcruple to hazard them to pleaſe themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Jealouſie of his Equals, the emulous ambition of his
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152882:46"/>potent Officers, and the ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Capricchio's of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Subjects, oblige a Prince to be always on his Guard with his Sword in Hand, to prevent thoſe Injuries which unprovided Security will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite them to offer him. And to compleat your Glory in matters of War, five things are chiefly requiſite; Armies, Forts, Garriſons, Proviſions, and Knowledge of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Places, and Humours of the Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>It was the Cuſtom of the Romans in the height of their Power, and is now the Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Cuſtom to bring prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous numbers of men into the field: but the great Victories the Romans obtained before
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152882:46"/>with ſmall numbers againſt vaſt multitudes of the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nations, And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Aſia</hi> by thoſe few Troops which made up <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders</hi> Army, do clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate that huge Bodies of Armed men are more for ſhow than ſervice; more fit for oſtentation, as Marks of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, than requiſite to bring Enterprizes to effect; which they obſtruct more by their confuſed multitudes, than they promote by their ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrength; Experience ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taught us, That the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part were Spectators only, not Actors in the Battel. This hath induced me to concur with the Modern Captains in their opinion, That thirty
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152882:47"/>thouſand Foot and four thouſand Horſe, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, may ſtand for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Army, without Exceſs or Defect, as a Number requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit to ſerve the Deſigns of a Prince, and ſufficient for the greateſt Undertakings, eaſier diſciplin'd, paid, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, than greater Bodies, moſt agreeable to the Modern Art of War. And as the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories obtained by ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Forces are more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, ſo in truth 'tis rare to ſee a place ſo free from Ditches, Rivers, Woods, Lakes, Mountains, and other Impediments, as to be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a greater Number in Battel Array.</p>
            <p>Beſides, We ſee that the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152882:47"/>Turk lays the ſtreſs of his Battels, and builds the Glory of his Victories, not on thoſe infinite multitudes which ſwell his Camp, but on the Valour and Experience of thoſe few Regiments of <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries</hi> that attend him, as <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> placed more confidence in his tenth Legion than in all the reſt of his Army, though the far greater Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and no mean Souldiers. And as <hi>Caeſar</hi> notwithſtanding the detriment by Battel and other Accidents, did by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſupplies preſerve that Legion always intire, ſo muſt a Prince take care by new for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to make up the number of thoſe Companies which the fate of War, the neceſſity of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152882:48"/>Garriſons, or other Occaſions, ſhall withdraw from his Army, which muſt be maintained in the full number we have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. And ſupplies of new men may be rationally thought to increaſe the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry of an Army, in that their want of experience makes them run more boldly into thoſe dangers which the try'd Souldier cunningly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines, or meets with cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Next the proportion of your Army, the Diſcipline of your Camp claims your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: And herein be ſure to eſtabliſh ſuch Rules that the Principles of Religion and Juſtice, may flouriſh there, that your Souldiers may pay
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152882:48"/>the Duty they owe to God, who is Lord of Hoſts, and to themſelves in a vertuous and honeſt Life, which muſt be attended with obedience and due reſpect to their General and all ſubordinate Officers: To effect this, encourage the Dutiful by Rewards and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and puniſh the Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and Contumacious by Diſgraces and Rigorous Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections. Stifle Mutinies in the Birth by ſharp Executions, as the beſt means to make impreſſions in Souldiers hearts, whom Rhetorique makes more inſolent. Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, as other men, have times of leaſure and vacation from the Exerciſes of the Camp; therefore to prevent the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152882:49"/>of Sloth and Idleneſs, 'tis the Generals part to invent ſuch Divertiſements as may by conſtant imployment ſecure them from thoſe Vices, and withal render Military En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements more familiar, and ſo leſs formidable to them. The duty of a Souldier is to obey willingly, and execute readily the Commands of his Officer: And that of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander is to act with Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Diſcretion, and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, to win them to a prompt obedience by Good Words, (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> call'd them Fellow-Souldiers) and by care of their Perſons, Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Credit, and Intereſt, which will oblige them upon occaſion to humble Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152882:49"/>and real Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
            <p>When you have thus ſettled the proportion and Diſcipline of your Army, you cannot rationally preſume of ſucceſs in your enterprizes, without good Rules and Orders for fight; which though they va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in this of War, as in other Arts, according to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent circumſtances of Action; yet Maximes grounded on Reaſon and Experience will fit a man to uſe all occaſions to beſt advantage: I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten obſerved a great diſorder in the Modern Diſcipline, and had an earneſt deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs it, which will appear to you by my large Collection of Notes to that purpoſe;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152882:50"/>but could never obtain lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from my Great Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to perfect my Deſign, which may deſerve the Pains of ſo great a Prince as you to compleat: The diſorder is, That our Battels and Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons are marſhalled in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Line, every particular Man, and the Ranks in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtanding directly behind one another; ſo that 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the firſt to retreat without diſturbance to the next Ranks: And thus the full ſtrength and effect of the Army, depends on the three or four firſt Ranks of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel. My deſign was, to find out a method whereby the firſt Rank being forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire might not bear upon the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152882:50"/>ſecond, nor the ſecond upon the third; but that the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Ranks might without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order or diſturbance readily ſtep forward into the place of the wearied men, and at once relieve them and engage the Enemy; ſo that no inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience may befall the Army upon the Retreat of the firſt Ranks; which I look as the chief Perfection of the Roman Diſcipline. To effect this, my project was, to divide the Vantguard-Battel and Rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard into three Squadrons, one to anothers ſide in a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angular Form; the firſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the point, the other two the ſides; for being thus diſ-joyned and ſevered by Art, it were eaſie to bring
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152882:51"/>forward the ſecond to fight, without diſturbing the firſt; and the third, without diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the other two: Whereby, beſides other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, the fortune of the Field will be thrice attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in one Encounter. And from this rough draught of the Deſign, you may proceed to an exact Method how theſe Squadrons being ſub-divided into ſmaller, may relieve one another with like Advantage, which Experience muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>Another Errour in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Diſcipline, is, That the beſt Souldiers are put in the firſt Ranks; whereby it comes to paſs that if theſe begin to ſhrink and give back, the reſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152882:51"/>by their example do the like, as if it were their Duty to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their Betters even in bad Actions; which hath been the Ruine not only of Companies and Regiments, but intire Armies: And herein the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans are worthy imitation, who placed in the Front thoſe they called <hi>Haſtati,</hi> or Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, conſiſting of young men of greateſt ſtrength and courage, mixed with a third part of old Souldiers, to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the heat, and direct the valour of the Youth; in the ſecond Squadron, called <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes,</hi> were two parts of old experienced Souldiers, and a third of young: The third called <hi>Triarii,</hi> was intirely made up of the moſt expert
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152882:52"/>and couragious in the Army. By this excellent Order it came to paſs, that not only the firſt on-ſet of the Roman Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being made by the warm Blood and emulous Courage of their choiceſt Youth, was violent and impetuous, and their Defence vigorous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt brisk Aſſaults; but that if at any time they gave back or were repulſed, the ſecond Squadron was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſuſtain the ſhock with greater Bravery; and upon their Retreat, the <hi>Triarii</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to maintain the fight, with aſſured hopes of Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to beat off thoſe Enemies who could not but be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly weakned by the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the <hi>Haſtati,</hi> and expert
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152882:52"/>Courage of the <hi>Principes.</hi> This Order I approve of, as of greateſt uſe. And though the high Reputation of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Arms may by their great and long ſucceſs in War, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the imitation of their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline without further Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; yet 'tis obvious to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Eye on what ſolid Grounds of Prudence this Order was eſtabliſhed, and that of the Greek <hi>Phalanges</hi> marſhalled in direct Lines rejected by the Romans, who though they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Rudiments of War from the Greeks, became greater Proficients in the Art than their Teachers; making themſelves Maſters of the one and the other, by conquering <hi>Greece</hi> with thoſe Arms the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152882:53"/>uſe whereof they derived from the Grecians. Another Argument for Collateral Squadrons, is, That the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>langes</hi> or Ranks marſhalled in a direct Line, are ſubject to greater Execution by the Enemies Artillery, which ſcours all that ſtands before it in a ſtrait Line. Beſides many other Obſervations which you will find ſcattered in my Notes for your dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this and other points of War.</p>
            <p>Nothing can render your Name more Illuſtrious than the Glory of perfecting this project for the better order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Forces in Battel. But let not your Employments at Land, make you forget that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152882:53"/>the Sea is part of your Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: Provide ſtores of all neceſſary Implements for Fleets; Let your Veſſels be well rigg'd, mann'd, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the ſervice of the State, and augmented to that number that may be ſufficient to ſerve your Deſigns, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out depending upon your Neighbours or Subjects. And never admit any Veſſel into the Liſt of your Fleets, but ſuch only wherein you have propriety: For private men are ſo wedded to their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt, that upon the appearance of danger their ſtudy is to preſerve their Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, though to the Ruine of the State.</p>
            <p>Cauſe your Forts to be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152882:54"/>often viewed, their works frequently ſurveyed, and ſee them repaired and improved where requiſite; and the Stores fill'd with all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Provide faithful, expert and couragious Governours, and truſty Souldiers: The Accidents of Death, Sickneſs, and loſs of men, will prompt you to exceed in number, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than fall ſhort; but make choice of ſuch as may give you cauſe, with the Romans, to rely more on the Valour of your Souldiers, than the ſtrength of the place, though never ſo well fortified by Art and Nature. Let your Forts on the Frontier be few but ſtrong. When you are aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, rather meet your Enemy
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152882:54"/>bravely in the Field, than coop your ſelf up in a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. When you are the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, chooſe to annoy the Enemy by Forts and Sconces raiſed for that purpoſe; and not with intolerable expence of Moneys and Time, and loſs of Men, to ſit down before his places of ſtrength, which ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom recompence your pains in the taking. In erecting Forts take your Model from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the place, and apply your Induſtry to make the whole proportionable to the parts, and the parts to the whole. And though no place can be impregnable, make yours of that ſtrength that may deprive the Enemy of hopes to take them without a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152882:55"/>tedious ſiege, great loſs of men, vaſt expence, and other diſadvantages that attend thoſe difficult Enterprizes.</p>
            <p>The Proviſions of War are Victuals, Artillery, Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Supplies, and Coyn; which are then ſufficient when the quantity ſeems to maintain an Army in a capacity to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any Martial Attempt; which had my weighty Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions permitted, I had reduced to a certainty. My project was, to raiſe a Gallant Army compoſed of <hi>Flemins, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> to be kept in conſtant exerciſe againſt the Turk and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes whom Danger or Intereſt ſhould oblige me to engage with. For their
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152882:55"/>Maintenance I deſign'd to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulate with them, That all Booties belonging to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe State, as Artillery, Ammunition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be intirely mine and my Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and all private Spoils to be diſtributed among the Souldiers; yet ſo, as to oblige them at reaſonable Rates to ſell to an Officer to be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to that purpoſe; ſuch Garments, Victuals, and other things of that nature, as were not neceſſary for preſent uſe, which ſhould be ſtored up by him, and ſold again to the Souldier upon occaſion with ſome profit to me. This had been of great conveniency to me, but more to the Souldier, in having at hand all Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152882:56"/>to ſupply his wants, at cheaper Rates than he could expect to receive them from thoſe who follow the Camp to raiſe their fortunes, and make unreaſonable Gains by exceſſive Prices.</p>
            <p>This done, my intention was, to conſtitute an Officer to receive and ſecure ſuch Moneys or Goods as the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier upon apprehenſion of any dangerous Service, or other conſideration, ſhould depoſit with him; and to be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the ſame to the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, his heirs and aſſigns with allowance of a reaſonable gain at ſo much <hi>per cent.</hi> for the uſe, with Proviſion that the goods of ſuch as died without Heirs, ſhould according to the courſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152882:56"/>of the Civil Law, belong to the Chamber of the Prince, and the like Conſtitution for ſuch as departed inteſtate: and what Souldier in the Army, whether private or in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, would not prefer the ſecuring of his Goods, where he, his Heirs or Aſſigns ſhould certainly receive them, before the expoſing them to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of Loſs by the Enemy, and other Accidents? And to defray the charge of Carriage requiſite for ſuch things, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance ſhould have been made by the Souldier out of the Gains to come to him from the Uſe. This Courſe will be of great Advantage to the Prince, who may make conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable profit of the Moneys
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152882:57"/>remaining in the hands of his Officers on this Account, to ſupply his Occaſions for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Army, and other neceſſary Charges, without injury to to the Proprietors: And beſides this, it will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the dependance of the Army upon him, the things depoſited being good Pledges of their Loyalty, and ſerve as an inexhauſtible Mine of Treaſure, by the Moneys and Goods of thoſe that die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out heirs and Inteſtate, or forfeit them by Diſloyalty.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Opinion that Moneys are the Sinews of War, you may believe it on my Experience, that it conduces much to the ſtrength of an Army well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152882:57"/>in all other things, but is far leſs neceſſary than good Diſcipline, Courage, Experience, and other Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions requiſite in well-order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Troops, and indeed of no efficacy in point of War where theſe are wanting. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think your ſelf more obliged to provide able Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, expert Souldiers, and good Orders for your Forces, than Moneys; the reaſon is, That ſuch an Army under the Conduct of a valiant and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent General, can never want means to maintain it ſelf by Pillage and Victuals, to be gained even in the heart of their Enemies Countrey. And though Proviſions may be ſometimes ſcant, the bare Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152882:58"/>of Pay and Rewards from a Prince in Reputation with his Army for Power to perform, and for keeping his Word, will keep them in heart in the greateſt Difficulties. 'Tis true, the nature of War is ſuch, whether offenſive or defenſive, and the Charge ſo exceſſive, that without ſome help 'twere impoſſible for a Prince to bear it; but the Courſes intimated before, and the Booty of rich Towns and Cities to be gained by Sieges or Stratagems, will render it tolerable and eaſie: And it muſt be your Care to make the War contribute to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of it ſelf, by employing your Forces in Actions atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Profit as well as
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152882:58"/>Honour, and declining all uſeleſs and unprofitable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes.</p>
            <p>Mortality and other Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents common to Man, make it impoſſible for an Army to ſubſiſt long intire in the ſame State without Supplies; in order to which, you are to cauſe frequent Muſters to be made in all Places of your Dominion, fit to yeild Supplies of men, and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to be kept of all the Youth able to bear Arms, where it may be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out apparent danger to the State by Tumult and Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And as your old Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers muſt be preſerved from Sloth by conſtant Exerciſes, ſo muſt the Youth that is to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152882:59"/>ſupply the Camp, be trained by ſufficient Leaders, for the Service of the War. In your choice, prefer thoſe who are naturally addicted to Arms; and amongſt them, chiefly thoſe who have Lands, Goods, or Relations to ſecure their Loyalty to your Crown, and implant in them a greater fear of ſhame or puniſhment, than can be expected from them who carry all their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts in their Perſons, and have nothing to care for but their own ſafety: But never preſs any man upon whom the ſubſiſtance of a Family de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, but ſuch onely who may be ſpared without great inconvenience, whom you are to encourage with hopes of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152882:59"/>Honour and Profit by the War.</p>
            <p>The Dominions you ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in, are ſo many and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, that they will eaſily furniſh you with means to raiſe and maintain a potent Army according to the Rules I have ſhewed; And if you keep good Correſpondence, and preſerve the Amity eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed between Us and our Allies of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> you will, beſides the <hi>Flemiſh, Italian,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have the <hi>Germans</hi> at your Devotion, who are a mighty and a brave People; and make your ſelf formidable to the greateſt Powers on Earth: Whereas if you be at Diſcord with your Kinſmen of that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152882:60"/>Houſe, it will impair your Authority, encourage your Enemies, weaken your Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and cool the Affections of your ancient Friends. Above all, have due regard, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs extraordinary reſpect for your Couſin the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as a perſon of ſo much worth, that the greateſt Empires are too narrow for the exerciſe of his Excellent Vertues. And obſerve it as a Maxime, That though matter of unkindneſs may ſometimes fall out between the neareſt Relations; yet more good may be hoped from the Love that ſprings out of Conſanguinity, than the faireſt pretences of Amity from a Stranger: And that it is more glorious to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152882:60"/>the Good Will and Friendſhip of your Kindred, by yeilding to them in ſome things to end differences, than by Arms to force Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to a Compliance with your Will.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point of training Youth, pleaſe their Humour, and encourage their love to War by Priviledges of wearing Weapons, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from the burdens of Civil Offices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Study an exact knowledge of the ſituation and nature of all places under your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, wherein their abundance conſiſts, and where their defects; ſupply theſe, and uſe the other as a means to eſtabliſh Amity between the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152882:61"/>ſeveral Members of your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, making the Abundance of one part to fill up the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the other: Cauſe Plots to be drawn of all their Places of ſtrength, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Rivers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That by reſorting to your Map, you may upon occaſion order mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with more certainty.</p>
            <p>Think it worth your pains to inquire not only into the Humours and Diſpoſitions, but the Intereſts, Alliances, and Factions of your potent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, for the Balance of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority remaining in your Hand, you may eaſily make that ſide moſt weighty and conſiderable that is beſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to your ſervice, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all diſorders that may
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152882:61"/>enſue upon their engagements in Parties againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>If any of your Countreys ſtand in danger of a Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Enemy, ſecure them from injury by your provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. And when you have an exact account of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, Power, Alliances, Intereſts, Wants, Stores, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Affections, Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Incommodities, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendancies, uſe all to your beſt advantage: Then conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the State and Power of thoſe you eſteem your Friends, or ſtand Neuters in the Quarrel: Weigh well the Perſons, Places, Times, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Cuſtoms, Neighbours, Officers, Adherents, and other
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152882:62"/>ſiderations incident to the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of your Foes and Friends. For nothing conduces more to a happy Victory, than a perfect knowledge of your own and your Enemies Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and a prudent uſe of that Knowledge. Be ſure you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver quarrel a great Potentate for relief of ſuch whoſe weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will rather endanger than aſſiſt your Crown, unleſs it appear that their Ruine may turn to your Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>In War, who ſpends moſt, makes leaſt waſte: Never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in a Quarrel but on juſt Grounds, and with prudent forecaſt of the Event; but when engaged, aſſure your ſelf 'tis never ſafe to dally or
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152882:62"/>delay. Make Proviſion ever in the beſt time, and of more than may ſeem neceſſary, for the loſs in the over-plus can be but ſmall; and though it were great, can bear no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the danger of of hazarding the greateſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings by want or ſcarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Victory is the mark of the Art Military, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in the beginning Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Diligence, and Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance; in the purſuit, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Perſeverance: Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſault firſt, than ſtay till you are ſet upon, and loſe the advantages of making War in your Enemies Countrey: If your Enemy prevent you herein, make Good your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and by all means endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152882:63"/>by diverſion to force him to retreat. Repoſe not the whole confidence of ſucceſs in your Armies at Land, nor Fleets at Sea, which are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to great uncertainties, as the Waves that bear them; but think Prudence and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the beſt means for Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and remember that at Sea commonly the greater Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber prevails <hi>Caeteris Paribus.</hi> But for your further Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in matter of War, I refer you to my Notes, which will afford you Rules for all Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. And now I ſhall apply my diſcourſe to the Enemies you are to grapple with, that you may perceive my ſence of their ſeveral Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and your Conduct in
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152882:63"/>your Wars againſt them.</p>
            <p>The Turk is your greateſt and moſt certain Enemy, both on the Account of Religion, which you are to prefer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other Intereſts; and that the violent Conſtitution of his Tyrannical Government keeps him always on his Guard, to ſecure his Power againſt ſudden Attempts; and ſo his Forces are ever in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be poured where hope of ſucceſs invites him, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires no other Cauſe of Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel. When I conſider the long courſe of <hi>Danubius,</hi> and the great Champaign of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> the ſituation of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and Neighbourhood of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> with the Power of the Neighbours on the one ſide,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152882:64"/>and the deſert Condition of the Borders on the other, I am induced to believe that he will wave the proſecution of his Conqueſts there for the preſent, and bend his Forces againſt the Iſlands, and your States in <hi>Italy,</hi> which he will aſſault before he breaks with <hi>Venice;</hi> the reaſon is, That if he fall on the Venetian firſt, he may expect greater Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition by ſuch Auxiliary For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as you may ſend in their Aid; but need not fear the Venetians engagement againſt him in your Quarrel in a time of peace with them, as well for that all Republiques, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ariſtocratical or Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical, flattering themſelves with hopes of a perpetual ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152882:64"/>do naturally decline all hazardous Undertakings; eſpecially when the Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they enjoy, and dangers of Action, repreſent every Alteration for the worſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the plauſible pretext of keeping their Faith inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the neceſſary depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the <hi>Venetian</hi> on the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire in point of Traffique; and the reaſons they have of being ſatisfied with their new Acqueſt of the Iſle of <hi>Candy</hi> from the Turk.</p>
            <p>The Turkiſh Empire hath its period, but known only to God; and 'tis in vain to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his Fall by Miracles from Heaven, which muſt be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by ſound Policies and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152882:65"/>ſtrength of Armed Men. The poor effects Experience hath ſhewed of an Univerſal League and Combination of Chriſtians againſt the Turks, afford you this Rule, That while men manage the Affairs of the World, they will often ſacrifice the beſt Cauſe and neareſt Concerns of true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to Humours and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; whereof you have a pregnant inſtance in the beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the French King on a cauſleſs Jealouſie in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand. This makes me conclude it a common Errour that the exceſſive Power of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> is to be humbled rather by the United Forces of ſeveral Princes, who cannot but have ſeveral Deſigns and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152882:65"/>ſeveral Intereſts, than by the ſtrength of one mighty Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, whoſe Deſigns are like his Perſon, ſingle and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and his Intereſt one and the ſame. This great Work ſeems reſerved for you, as the greateſt Prince of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Profeſſion; and with the Aid of your Allies of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Ability to encounter that Pagan Giant; but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſerious Conſideration of the moſt proper means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your ends, by ſuch ways as ſound experimental Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhall direct.</p>
            <p>And firſt what War is moſt available againſt him, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive or Offenſive, by Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or by Diverſion? As for
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152882:66"/>Defenſive War, nothing but pure Neceſſity can juſtifie the choice of it; being the moſt unprofitable, uncomfortable, and dangerous, as that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we do but expoſe and lay our ſelves open to the injuries of Hoſtility, to the manifeſt conſumption of our ſtrength, and to the apparent danger of our whole Intereſt, without hope of Reſtitution of Loſs, or Reparation of Damages.</p>
            <p>The impoſſibility of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Preparations requiſit for an Offenſive War, without the knowledge of the Turk, and finding him on his guard, may diſſwade you from that courſe; as the multitude of Forces he maintains in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant pay, and always in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152882:66"/>anticipates all Deſigns to moleſt him, by preventive Wars, or by way of Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; ſo that my Advice is, To avoid the ſimple kinds of War, and to reſolve on a mixt, Defenſive in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but Offenſive in act; which if wiſely managed, may by degrees of Prevention and Diverſion, be at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into a pure Offenſive; which muſt be effected more by ſlights and ſtratagems, than plain force, againſt this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Enemy: And to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you will find frequent Opportunities by the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Encombrances of his other Wars, his Loſſes, and the Diſorders of his Camp, and the Diſcord about the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152882:67"/>ſucceſſion of the Empire. But rely chiefly on the favour of God, which is partly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the uſe of means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by humane Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as conducing moſt to the ends we aim at; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you are to preſerve the Affections of your Allies of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to your Perſon and Intereſt. And as the ſtate of their Affairs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but oblige them to a ſtrict Correſpondence and Amity with you for the better At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement of their Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes; ſo you are to believe that to maintain Friendſhip and Good Intelligence with them, will not only ſtrengthen your Intereſt in general, but is of abſolute neceſſity in
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152882:67"/>order to Succeſs againſt the Turk.</p>
            <p>Accompt that your beſt time of war with the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> when he is engaged with ſome potent Enemy elſe where, or perplexed with dangers and ſeditions, diſcontents or factions at home: But if the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Affairs cannot conveniently allow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of theſe opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, when your preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have given him the Alarm, and drawn his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into the field, make uſe of ſhifts and delayes to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his deſigns by declin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing engagement, and putting upon him the loſs of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152882:68"/>whole expence of that <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagn:</hi> And the next year take the advantage of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, want of preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſability to appear on the ſudden in compleat equipage: And be ſure to march forward with all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, that you may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your new Conqueſts, and be in a capacity to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them againſt him by a reſolute defence before he advances to ſtop your courſe: and diſpoſe your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, ſo that when he begins to diſband and draw off into his quarters, you may be ready to fall on: And by renewing the war, put him on the neceſſity of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152882:68"/>his vaſt Armies in pay, (which he can by no means endure long,) or reduce his Army to ſo mean a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, as may give you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hopes of victory.</p>
            <p>No place is fitter for the ſeat of the war, than in ſome parts of <hi>Hungary</hi> remote from <hi>Danubius;</hi> for beſides the narrowneſs of ſeveral pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſages extremely incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for the huge bodys of his Cavalry, He will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of thoſe Convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which the River affords for that immence baggage, and cumberſome train uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally attending his Camp, whereof you may make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe to the benefit of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152882:69"/>your, and prejudice, if not ruine of his deſigns. And to that purpoſe, I again Commend to you a good Correſpondence with your Uncle the King of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> to whom you are to Grant and offer all Aydes of men or mony to keep the ballance even, till you find an opportunity to appear in the field.</p>
            <p>The Turk relies intirely on the number and ſtrength of his men: And your way to defeat him being by ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem; be carefull to draw him into ſtraight and narrow places, where he cannot for want of room make uſe of his whole power. And
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152882:69"/>may be pinched for defect of Carriages, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proviſions. In Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Conflicts, provide Stout Companies of Foot to annoy his horſe; who being generally without Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, are ſoon routed by the ſtrong impreſſions of a Gallant infantry. 'Tis a point of the Turkiſh diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, to reſerve the Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries for the laſt onſet and recourſe to victory: And if a choice ſequadron be pickt out to engage them, from the beginning to the end of the battle; the unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the ſtratagem will ſurprize, and much diſorder the Janizaries, and abate
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152882:70"/>the courage of the reſt of their Army, who are never out of hopes of victory, till the Janizaries are engaged and repulſed. By this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy <hi>Hannibal</hi> gained ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral victories againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans:</hi> And to it the <hi>Romans</hi> owe theirs over the <hi>Latines.</hi> Uſe all indeavours to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite the people to Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt him, by good uſage, immunities, exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or by building ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires and forts fit for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and offence; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you will find excellent inſtructions in my memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls for ſpeed and cheapneſs, and in the work their beſt uſe when perfected, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152882:70"/>the forces of a great eſtate; whereof <hi>Caeſars</hi> acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>France</hi> are an inſtance, as related in the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries: And you may eſteem the leaſt declination of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> power, a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to your affairs, by the opportunity it affords his ſuppreſſed ſubjects to endeavour the recovery of their loſt liberties, which his tyranical government makes them willing to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, when invited by a fit occaſion.</p>
            <p>The ſolid ſtrength of the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> receives addition of power by the willingneſs of other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (and eſpecially the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152882:71"/>
               <hi>Italians</hi>) jealous of our forces, to Aſſiſt that Crown againſt us: threfore let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider next the beſt way of making war upon the <hi>French.</hi> Had they known to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the taking of <hi>Caſab,</hi> or <hi>Revolt</hi> of <hi>Sienna</hi> to the beſt advantage, we had felt e're this by dear experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, how much the <hi>Italians</hi> are inclined to novelty; and the great benefit the <hi>French</hi> may obtain with inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable charge in the wars of <hi>Italy:</hi> For though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be doubted, but that the Government of the <hi>French,</hi> if poſſeſſed of thoſe places we hold in <hi>Italy,</hi> would in a ſhort time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152882:71"/>more offenſive and inſupportable to the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, than ours: yet ſuch is their itch of change, ſo great their jealouſies of our forces in <hi>Milan, Naples,</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily</hi> that they throw open their Armes to receive any that promiſes to reſtore their liberty, which they think loſt in the fetters of our power, in the places I have named. But 'tis your happineſs, that by aſſaulting that King in his own domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions (which you can eaſily doe) you will infallibly force him to recall his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from <hi>Italy,</hi> to defend <hi>France:</hi> And gladly imploy them to quench the fire
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152882:72"/>kendled in his own houſe, whom he had commanded to burn yours. It hath been their maxime long, not to leave an Enemy behind them: it muſt be yours to winn, and fortifie ſome place of importance in their paſſage to <hi>Italy,</hi> which may either ſtop their farther march, or at leaſt entertain their forces ſo long, till yours be in readineſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them by defence, or ſtop them by diverſion.</p>
            <p>To this end, it was my deſign to build two or three forts between <hi>Turine</hi> and the <hi>Alps,</hi> of that Art and ſtrength, that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght deter the <hi>French</hi> from attempting <hi>Italy</hi> that way, by the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152882:72"/>of reducing thoſe places to their obedience at ſo great diſtance from their Country: But this (as other deſignes) was prevented by my imployments elſe where: So that I propoſe it only, as worthy your conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and haſten to give you brief rules for your wars in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That King may be aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his own Country two wayes, by taking ſome ſtrong places upon the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, or by entring the heart of his Dominions with a compleat Army, and making your ſelf Maſter of the field. But the ſtrength of his Towns and Caſtles
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152882:73"/>on the borders, the vaſt expence, and tedious diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Sieges, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant charge and great Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons requiſite to maintain and preſerve them in your obedience, when taken; and the opportunities given him to Muſter his forces, and make defence, before you can probably reduce the place you attaque; may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you to wave that courſe, and embrace the latter: and the rather, for that you have the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of Arming a great deal ſooner than he; And thruſt your forces into the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of his Kingdom, before he can be in readineſs to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152882:73"/>come into the field: And that his Country abounds ſo much with Victuals and other proviſion, that an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my cannot want in ſo great plenty: And needs only uſe its power to maintain it ſelf by the ſpoils of the enemy. You cannot expect by one Aſſault, to break the force of ſo compact a Body as the Kingdom of <hi>France;</hi> but think that expedition well made, wherein you become Maſter of a Limb, and bring ſome ſmall part to your obedience; if you make good your ground, and retain firmly what you gain by peicemeal, every ſtep you make advances you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152882:74"/>towards the Conqueſt of the whole. This was <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> method in ſubduing that Nation. When you have once got footing there, a thouſand opportunities from the diſtraction of that ſtate, by their diviſions and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocities in matter of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the ambition of the great ones, and other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, will preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for improvement of your intereſt. The Sun though he moves inſenſibly, doth compaſs the world in 24 houres. And common ſence informs, you that the ſmalleſt particle taken from the leſſer quantity, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the greater, Auge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152882:74"/>the one, and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes the other: which I mind you of, that you may not be diſcouraged, though you cannot on the ſudden overcome this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but perſevere in the proſecution of your deſign upon this Aſſurance, that by gaining the parts, you will at laſt Maſter the whole.</p>
            <p>If the French Kings mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions give you cauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that by the advantage of the ſeaſon, and forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Country, he may enter <hi>Italy</hi> ſome moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Army can arrive in <hi>France;</hi> Make ſhew of early, and great preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt <hi>France,</hi> to march
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152882:75"/>thither as ſoon as the ſeaſon of the year will permit: And by this ſtratagem you will oblige him to uſe thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for defence at home, which he deſigned for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Conqueſts: So jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous is he of that Kingdom; So contrary is it to the Maxims of his Policy, to leave his frontiers unguard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an Army, when threatned with hoſtility from abroad, or to expoſe his Kingdom to an invation, in the abſence of any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of his forces.</p>
            <p>When you have reſolved on either of theſe courſes of war with <hi>France,</hi> take heed of wavering from your
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:152882:75"/>choice, as a thing moſt diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to your affairs: and avoyd it as a Rock ſhewed you by a Pilot, whoſe ſhip was ſplit thereon. I entred <hi>France</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Landrecy,</hi> with full purpoſe to have advanced into the heart of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, before the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to their ayd, but the altering of this reſolution in my ſtay, to winn ſome Towns on the frontiers (which detained me longer than I expected, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by the facility of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the firſt I attaiqued,) gave the King time enough to provide ſtrength ſufficient to encounter me; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo fatal in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152882:76"/>that I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by plain force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and yield to conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which (to be free with you) ſerved only for a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of retreat, without any advantage to my affairs.</p>
            <p>Purſue your victories in <hi>France</hi> effectually, and with diligence: And having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them to ſeek Ayds from abroad, fall on them afreſh before the Auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Arive: And when the ſucceſs anſwers not your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, repair your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hold them ſo long in play, till the ſeaſon of the year make them deſpair of any advantage to be made in <hi>Italy</hi> by your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat:
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152882:76"/>Rely not on the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but choice of your men; and prefer a gallant, though ſmall Army, before a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: and againſt <hi>France</hi> make ſpecial poviſion of ſtrong Companys of foot to encounter their horſe.</p>
            <p>I will reiterate my advice againſt ſiting down with your forces before any place of ſtrength that may require a long ſiege, unleſs invited by correſpondence within, or ſome other particular advantage, that gives aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hopes of diſpatch: and that not only for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons given before, but that it is a matter of extream dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, to maintain an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152882:77"/>long at a ſiege, where convenient room is not made for the Convoys. My randezvous a <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated my deſign againſt <hi>Provence,</hi> and opened the eyes of the French King to ſpy his advantage, by diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in <hi>Turine;</hi> where he made war with ſecurity, forced me to retreat with great danger, gained credit with the States of <hi>Italy</hi> by the action, and had hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the eſtates you hold there, had he known as well to uſe, as perform his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings.</p>
            <p>The difficulty of recruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Armies in <hi>Italy</hi> by ſupplies from <hi>Spain,</hi> when
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152882:77"/>requiſite, upon any miſadven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and the propenſity of thoſe States to Revolt from you, muſt incline you by aſſaulting <hi>France,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that King from caſting his thoughts to diſturb you in <hi>Italy;</hi> rather than to be on the diſadvantage of an after gain, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling him from thence: And aſſure your ſelf, that States, and eſpecially the <hi>Italian,</hi> have no affection but for their intereſt, and will ſtick to you, to their own prejudice or danger, but will be ready upon the leaſt appearance of your declining, to eſpouſe the quarrel of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152882:78"/>party, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the fortune of the Conqueror. Bend all your force to recover <hi>Sienna,</hi> that other States may by that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, perceive and fear the danger of ſlighting your Authority, and intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with ſtrangers, to the prejudice of your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: And that you may by that means cut of the Correſpondence between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Get perfect information of the affections, humours and intereſts of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in greateſt favour and credit with the French King, and the competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for great offices, and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152882:78"/>uſe the beſt means to gain the ſtrongeſt parties to your devotion; as the neceſſary and moſt excellent inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to promote your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. In alliances and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Eſteem the removal of the <hi>French</hi> from <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> above millions of Crowns in Dower, or the moſt ample conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in a league: And indeavour earneſtly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to a deſuetude from Arms, and a forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of military exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. And when an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity is offered to your advantage, loſe it not: As to <hi>Piedmont</hi> I will repeat my advice for
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152882:79"/>recovery of it; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it from my experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to be of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to your affairs, than if on the Flemiſh ſide you had bereaft the French King of a third part of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Your intereſt in <hi>Italy,</hi> is the main Artery by which the pulſe of all your power beats: And wherein lyes the greateſt miſtery of your Policy: therefore muſt your eyes be ever open that way, even to Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: To preſerve it the better, Uſe all devotion and kindneſs to the Pope and Apoſtlick See; Be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to all the Cardinals,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152882:79"/>Biſhops, Prelats and other members of the Court, and ever ready to defend them, and the Catholique profeſſion. In the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Popes, when all the competitors are worthy of the dignity; Strive not to advance one before the other: And never uſe any means indirect, unlawfull or unchriſtian, to prefer your friends or creatures to the Chair; but look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a ſacred action to be left as the election of <hi>Mathias</hi> in the tent, to the diſpoſal of the Holy Ghoſt. The expreſſion of due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects attended, with the conſideration of your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152882:80"/>ſituate in the midſt of <hi>Italy,</hi> and other means in your power, as King of ſo many Countrys, and Patron of ſo many great Eccleſiaſtical benefices, will infallibly procure you the friendſhip of the greateſt, and make the beſt amongſt them dependants upon you, without loſs or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to Princes of your quality, though the Pope were elected by the votes of that party, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for another. But let me enjoyn you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer alwayes the univerſal good of Chriſtendom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your private benefit, though the Examples of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152882:80"/>others ſeem to invert the Counſel I give you. As the Dominions of the Church, are the center of <hi>Italy;</hi> So, if <hi>Sienna</hi> were recovered, they would be ſurrounded with your Territories to the greater convenience for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and moſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for an influence over the Court of <hi>Rome:</hi> If men of Piety ſit in the Chair, they will in a religious ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of promoting Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among Chriſtians, both court and deſire your love: if the Popes be worldly minded, and ſtudy more their pleaſures and intereſt, then the duties of their
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152882:81"/>office, (which God forbid) they will be glad to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his friendſhip, whom they dare not diſpleaſe. Stick not to powre the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your bounties on that Court, in obliging the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Biſhops, and other Prelates, by dignities and preferments in your ſeveral Dominions; but eſpecially them who are moſt intimate with the Pope, as moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in matters of grace and favour to be obtained from the Holy-Chair: though you are to rely moſt on the Juſtice and equity of your Demands, and the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his Holineſs.</p>
            <p>The impreſſions of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152882:81"/>are ſo deep in the hearts of men, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can prejudice your affairs more, than to leave in their minds an opinion of your being diſaffected to the Miniſters of God: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if neceſſity force you to break with the Pope, be ſure to clear your ſelf from the imputation of the rupture, by making it appear, that the cauſe of unkindneſs proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not from you, but from the other ſide: And that the courſe you take is not voluntary, but upon indiſpenſable obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſecurity and ſelf preſervation. In matters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152882:82"/>to a Generall Councel, conform your ſelf to the determinations of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Chair; and whatever happens, let the world ſtill perceive your Religion is unchangeable.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> you are ſure of Peace with them, while you think fit not to break the league; by reaſon of their fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs to engage in war, though no aſſiſtance is to be expected from them for the reaſons I have ſhewed. And that jealouſie, and apprehenſions of ill from the increaſe of power, will have greater influence in their counſells, than any
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:152882:82"/>other conſiderations. Their long neglect of military diſcipline, and diſuſe of Arms, their letting ſlip ſo many brave opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, the diſtractions of this age afforded them to Aggrandize their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, may invite you to aſſault them; and their cuſtome of making ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their weak neighbours miſeries, may in a manner juſtifie it. A ſlothfull diſpoſition and moderate proſperity, have inclined them to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, their greatneſs may be maintained by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of peace and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber rules of the Long
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152882:83"/>robe. But if you ſet upon them briſkly, and purſue your firſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion with Celerity to prevent their band<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with other Princes; their unſkilfullneſs in war, the weakneſs of their ſtate, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions that will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend their fear of your Arms, will give you opportunity to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs ſome great exploit before they awake out of ſleep, or reſolve what to ſpend, what friends to truſt, what Leaders to employ, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their old diſcipline for war. The conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152882:83"/>they have to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque you in <hi>Naples,</hi> and the inclinations of that people, to prefer their mild, and more civil Government, and kind uſage of the inhabitants, before yours; will oblige you to get the ſtart of them by carrying the war to their doors, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their attempts againſt your Dominions, by force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to provide for defence of their own: Let it be your care to powre your forces into the center of their ſtate as the way to make your ſelf maſter of the field, it being impoſſible for
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152882:84"/>them to put Garriſons into their places of ſtrength, which they will firſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and at the ſame time to keep the field: And in the mean while the defect of Garriſons, Leaders proviſions or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, the factions and particular diſcontents of perſons intereſſed, will certainly afford you the occaſion, to poſſeſs your ſelf of ſome of their places of ſtength; which will be a good ſtep to your further progreſs, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if by your Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Gracious deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you encourage others to ſubmit to your
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152882:84"/>obedience, by granting the Burghers, Captains and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers reaſonable Articles, and ſo good conditions, that they will have no juſt cauſe to complain of the change of Maſters. When you are Maſter of the field, all places that are not ſtrong will preſently fall into your hands; which will force them into the field to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the ſtopping of your prevailing Arms by battail, wherein the greatneſs of your ſtrength, and expert ſkill of your Soldiers, may give you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hopes of victory over their new trayned
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152882:85"/>troops and raw Companies.</p>
            <p>Let no pretence of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or profeſſions of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from any Prince of <hi>Italy,</hi> move you to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to aggrandize his ſtate; but be perſwaded by my advice, to keep them all within their due bounds, upon this infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ground, that they are true only to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and will no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adhere to you, then while it is for their turn, but will appear againſt you, upon any proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hope to better their fortune. The diviſions, and partialities of <hi>Italy,</hi> make it a matter of great
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152882:85"/>difficultie for you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in your obedience the States you enjoy there, their deſigns, and moſt ardent deſires, being bent to eſtabliſh a Duke at <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain;</hi> and a King at <hi>Naples,</hi> which may hold of no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, but reign Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and Independant, as the means to weaken your encroaching power, and to free themſelves from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign ſervitude: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may upon all occaſions treat on even terms, with ſuch petty Princes; and that the bonds of a common inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which is the ſureſt obligation, would ingage
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152882:86"/>a King of <hi>Naples,</hi> and a Duke of <hi>Milan,</hi> in a forreign league of Friendſhip with them, againſt forreign force, as involved in the like dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, with other States of <hi>Italy,</hi> of being oppreſt from abroad; whereas the ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quallity between them and you, is ſuch that they neither dare engage in a war againſt you, for fear of loſing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of their liberty, and making their eſtates victims to your wrath; nor enter into a league, to add ſtrength to your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which they deſire to ſee weakned, and increaſe your Authority, whereof
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:152882:86"/>they are allready jealous. The Pope and <hi>Venetians</hi> are great promoters of the project I have told you; but the remedy is obvious to prevent their deſignes: for if you maintain your reputation, by a conſtant Activity in Armes, hold good intelligence in every State; Imploy able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> make uſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and factions of thoſe Princes to your advantage, prevent combinations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice; keep out the French King from <hi>Italy;</hi> and when the waters are troubled diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly uſe the Golden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hook,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:152882:87"/>you may conclude your affairs ſafe on that ſide.</p>
            <p>Theſe obſervations moſt dear Son I leave with you, as Rules for your conduct in Peace and War; And though the circumſtances of things may vary, yet the reaſon of my advice, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining the ſame, will be uſeful for direction in moſt occurrences of State. And now by the duty and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude you owe me your Father, your Prince and Benefactor, I charge you ſtrictly, and conſtantly to obſerve with Reverence, the Laws of God and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to regard them as the controll of your reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:152882:87"/>and Rules of indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſable obligation in all your actions, that no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, no act, no ſtratagem can be juſt or worthy a Prince but what is conſonant to them: And amidſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick Glories of a mighty Prince, forget not your ſelf to be a man, and that the prerogative of your Crowns exempts you from the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of thoſe tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, where bribery may corrupt, affections blind, ignorance miſlead, fear over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe, or impotence fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the judgement given, to reſerve your cauſe to the dreadfull examination and ſentence of that Judge,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:152882:88"/>who is Juſtice it ſelf, and cannot be deceived; who for the ſins of Princes gives their dominions to whom he pleaſes, without other reſpects to their Crowns, than to aggravate their offence in abuſing the priviledges of their State, to the contempt of his Juſtice and preſuming to commit ſuch trangreſſions againſt his Laws, which they would not permit to be done by their Subjects againſt theirs. And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you are to account to a Judge, from whom there is no appeal, who inflicts heavieſt puniſhments on wicked Princes, as immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:152882:88"/>offenders againſt his Majeſty, and therefore moſt fit to be made examples of Juſt Severity; as Good Kings are the immediate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his care and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, partake moſt of his bounty and favours, and are in affection no leſs then in dignity, nearer to God than other mortals.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:89"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:89"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:90"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152882:90"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
